Guide to the Betsy Beinecke Shirley Collection of American Children's Literature
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Betsy Beinecke Shirley collection of American children's literature
1640-2001
GEN MSS 764
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
19.5
(53 boxes) + 3 broadside folders + 7 art objects
Collection consists of manuscripts (correspondence and drafts of writings), illustration material (drawings in all media, photographs, book dummies, and printing blocks and plates), and publication proofs by various authors and artists including Louisa May Alcott, Alexander Anderson, Louis-Maurice Boutet de Monvel, Gelett Burgess, Harrison Cady, Palmer Cox, F. O. C. Darley, W. W. Denslow, Jo Mora, Peter Newell, and Symeon Shimin, as well as work produced for the McLoughlin Brothers publishing house. Also present are penmanship exercise books, samplers, and other school work produced by American children including John Hancock and his brother Ebenezer, letters of advice written to children by prominent figures such as Samuel Clemens, Charles Dodgson, Benjamin Franklin, and George Washington, and writings created by and for Native American children.
Shirley, Betsy Beinecke
Alcott, Louisa May, 1832-1888
Anderson, Alexander, 1775-1870
André, R. (Richard), 1834-1907
Angelo, Valenti, 1897-1982
Anglund, Joan Walsh, 1926-
Bemelmans, Ludwig, 1898-1962
Billings, Hammatt, 1818-1874
Boutet de Monvel, Louis Maurice, 1850-1913
Boutet de Monvel, Roger, 1879-
Bowles, Carington, 1724-1793
Bransom, Paul, 1885-1979
Bruton, W. (William), 1854 or 1855-1885
Burgess, Gelett, 1866-1951
Cady, Harrison, 1877-1970
Capote, Truman, 1924-1984
Church, Frederick S. (Frederick Stuart), 1842-1924
Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910
Cogger, Edward P.
Cox, Palmer, 1840-1924
Cruikshank, George, 1792-1878
Darley, Felix Octavius Carr, 1822-1888
Denslow, W. W. (William Wallace), 1856-1915
Dodgson, Charles Lutwidge, 1832-1898
Drayton, Grace G. (Grace Gebbie), 1877-1936
Falls, C. B. (Charles Buckles), 1874-1960
Field, Eugene, 1850-1895
Francis, J. G. (Joseph Greene), 1849-1930
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
Frost, A. B. (Arthur Burdett), 1851-1928
Furness, William Henry, 1802-1896
Grimaldi, Stacey, 1790-1863 ( Toilet)
Goodwin, Polly, 1908-2007
Gruelle, Johnny, 1880-1938
Hale, Sarah Josepha Buell, 1788-1879
Hancock, Ebenezer, 1741-1819
Hancock, John, 1737-1793
Hopkins, Livingston, 1846-1927
Ives, Sarah Noble, 1864-1944
Keller, Helen, 1880-1968
Kemble, E. W. (Edward Windsor), 1861-1933
Lathrop, Dorothy Pulis, 1891-1980
McVickar, H. W. (Harry Whitney), 1860-
Melvill, Allan, 1782-1832
Moore, Clement Clarke, 1779-1863
Mora, Jo, 1876-1947
Newell, Peter, 1862-1924
Petersham, Maud, 1890-1971
Pogány, Willy, 1882-1955
Reynolds, Cuyler, 1866-1934
Rogers, W. A. (William Allen), 1854-1931
Sands, Benjamin
Shimin, Symeon, 1902-1984
Shinn, Everett, 1876-1953
Smith, Jessie Willcox, 1863-1935
Sperry, J. Austin (Jacob Austin), 1823-1896
Stephens, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1824-1882
Stratemeyer, Edward, 1862-1930
Twain, Mark, 1835-1910
Tyler, Mary Elizabeth Sawyer, 1806-1889
Tyrrell, Leon M., b. 1875
Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1882-1944
Washington, George, 1732-1799
Webster, Noah, 1758-1843
Whiting, Mary Elizabeth Flint, b. 1823
Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892
Wiese, Kurt, 1887-1974
Johnson & Warner
McLoughlin Bros
Nazareth Hall
Peekskill Military Academy (Peekskill, N.Y.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts and bequest of Betsy Beinecke Shirley, 1989-2005.
Custodial History
The collection was transferred to Beinecke Library in a series of gifts made over several years, with the remainder of the material transferred by her estate following her death in 2004. Some of the paintings and drawings featured in the published catalog Drawn to Enchant: Original Children's Book Art in the Betsy Beinecke Shirley Collection (New Haven, CT: Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 2007) were passed along to family members and therefore are not included in this finding aid.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 49-50: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Betsy Beinecke Shirley's collections of children's books and serials, published prints, printed ephemera, and commercially produced objects (including toys, games, and printed kerchiefs) were cataloged separately. They can be accessed through the library's online catalog, Orbis, using the term "Shirley" in the "Call Number (Local)" search field.
Betsy Beinecke Shirley (1919-2004)
Betsy Beinecke Shirley was born in New York City, on October 2, 1919, the daughter of Walter and Katherine Sperry Beinecke. Raised in the city and on Nantucket, Massachusetts, she attended the Spence School in Manhattan, and the Greenwood School in Ruxton, Maryland, after which, in 1941, she married Carl Shirley (1916-1996). Betsy Shirley began collecting American juvenile literature in the 1970s, eventually branching out to encompass original illustrations and manuscripts for children's books, as well as manuscripts, correspondence, and drawings by and about American children, their education, imagination, and play. The Betsy Beinecke Shirley Collection of American Children's Literature grew to hold thousands of volumes of books and serials, and hundreds of manuscript items and works of original art, many of which were displayed throughout her home in Bernardsville, New Jersey. A trustee of the Newark Museum for many years, she regularly lent books and original illustrations to museum and library exhibitions, including A Child's Garden of Dreams at the Brandywine River Museum (1989-1990), which was drawn entirely from her collection. Betsy Shirley died in Bernardsville on September 4, 2004.
Scope and Contents
The collection holds the non-print component of the Betsy Beinecke Shirley Collection of American Children's Literature, and contains original illustrations and manuscript material acquired by Betsy Shirley to complement and enhance her extensive collection of printed books and serials. It consists of drawings, paintings, literary manuscripts, printing blocks, correspondence, and documents related to children's literature, and the education and amusement of children. In accordance with her views as a collector, the material was divided between that created for literary purposes by both professionals and amateurs (in Series I) and that of a more historical nature and related to education (in Series II). Series III holds three small collections of papers that were acquired as discrete archival groups: the papers of J. Austin Sperry, Leon M. Tyrrell, and Edward Stratemeyer.
In this finding aid, the term "drawing" indicates an original work of illustration art, and does not distinguish the stages between a preliminary sketch and a finished drawing; for some artists, such as F. O. C. Darley, there are both present. Every attempt was made to assign a specific title, project, or publication to the illustrations in the collection. Original works of art are filed under the artist's name, regardless if the resulting publication is more prominently associated with the author of the text; for example, drawings by Frederick Richardson for Andrew Lang's popular fairy book volumes appear here under Richardson's name.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Authors and Illustrators for Children (1719-2001); II. American History and Educational Materials (1640-1966); and III. Other Papers (1836-1968).
Art -- Collectors and collecting; Books -- Pirated editions; Children -- Conduct of life; Children's art; Children's literature, American; Children's writings; Illustration of books -- 19th century; Illustration of books -- 20th Century; Illustrators; Indians of North America -- Missions; Picture books for children; Pressed flower pictures; Wild flowers -- Palestine; Alaska -- Description and travel; Alaska -- Gold discoveries; Advertising cards; Albums (Books); Ambrotypes (photographs); Visiting cards; Diaries; Drawings (visual works); Dummies (Publishing); Exercise books; Gem photographs; Hand-colored illustrations; Harlequinades (books); Juvenilia; Juvenile literature; Medals; Oil paintings (visual works); Pen and wash drawings; Penmanship specimen books; Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Poetry; Rewards of merit; Samplers (embroidery); Scrapbooks; Watercolors (paintings); Wood blocks (printing blocks); Shirley, Betsy Beinecke; American Baptist Missionary Union. Assam Mission; Santa Claus
- Authors and Illustrators for Children, 1719-2001; Series I; 8.38; (21 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically. Works by unidentified artists and authors are filed at the end, followed by a small group of wood and metal printing blocks and plates.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains writings and illustrations related to literary efforts which were created by both professional and amateur writers and artists, primarily but not exclusively American. Found here are manuscripts, drawings, correspondence, and documents prepared by professionals for pay, publishers, or publication, and meant to be distributed to thousands of readers. Of note are the more than one hundred drawings by Palmer Cox featuring his trademark Brownies and Greenies, who scampered across pages in serials, drug company trade catalogs, and Cox's own books, puzzles, and toys; more than one hundred drawings and sketches by Felix Octavius Carr Darley to illustrate novels by the various popular authors he teamed with, including James Fenimore Cooper; more than three hundred drawings by Gelett Burgess of his silly but instructive characters the Goops; and a set of forty-four silhouettes drawn by Livingston Hopkins to illustrate Thomas Bailey Aldrich's translation of Emile de la Bédollière's The Story of a Cat (1878). In his preface, Aldrich praises Hopkins' "ingenious and spirited" drawings which he equates in importance to his contribution to the publication.
  Also here are single and intimate literary efforts by non-professionals that were meant to be viewed and treasured by family members and friends. Two charming examples are manuscript versions of the popular volume The Toilet: a Book for Young Ladies, by Stacey Grimaldi, published in London in 1821, and thought to be one of the earliest works in the "flap book" format. Grimaldi wrote a series of short verses to illustrate images of toilet articles drawn by his father William; each image incorporated a flap that, when raised, revealed a virtue, such as perseverance, intimated by the poem. The manuscript copies here were made by unidentified young women in New Brunswick, New Jersey, and Charleston, South Carolina, no doubt for their friends to enjoy as a parlor activity. Another example is a small bound volume titled "Aunt Mary's Stories," written and illustrated by Mary Keely expressly for her nephews William Mason Bailey (1841-1893) and Charles Emerson Bailey (1843-1912) of Waterville, Maine.
  Some of the works present are a combination: created by a professional artist for a single person, such as the more than fifty heavily decorated letters and notes written by the painter Frederick Stuart Church to members of the Schley family of New York City and Far Hills, New Jersey, who were among his great patrons. The recipients were Grant (1845-1917) and Elizabeth Baker Schley (1843-1910), their daughter Evelyn Baker Schley (1885-1919) and her husband Max H. Behr (1884-1955), and the Behrs' daughters Lisbeth (born 1906) and Evelyn Shirley (born 1908). Church's letters describe his activities and occupations, including restoration he performed on some of the Schley family's Old Master paintings, and are embellished with whimsical ink, watercolor, and crayon drawings, as well as a few photographs and etchings he glued on the pages.
  In addition to American writers and illustrators, Betsy Shirley was also interested in American publishers who pirated works produced in other countries, and in general, documenting the various stages in producing books for children. The series holds examples showing that New York's McLoughlin Brothers re-purposed images printed in England. The files for Maud Fuller and Miska Petersham include drawings, proof sheets, and book dummies for two of their popular volumes, and there are two book dummies for titles illustrated by Symeon Shimin. Also present are a small group of engraved wood blocks and metal printing plates used in the production of children's books, as well as for a bookplate by W. W. Denslow.
  - Abbott, Jacob
    - Correspondence: letter to unidentified recipient, enclosing four holograph pages from Minigo; letter to Benson Lossing, regarding A Primary History of the United States; and fragment of letter to unidentified recipient, 1857, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Contracts and agreements signed on Abbott's behalf by his son and lawyer Austin Abbott, 1870-1879 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adams, William T. (William Taylor)
    - Letters (2) to Henry Cleveland and Laird Simons, regarding writings, 1871, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alcott, Louisa May
    - Correspondence: letters to Clementia Taylor, regarding Louisa May Nieriker; to Thomas Bailey Aldrich, regarding poem by friend; and postcard to Mrs. R. F. Bassett, regarding costume party, 1880-1885 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript leaves of Jack and Jill; holograph; pages 29 and 122, published as 18 and 87, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript leaf of Jo's Boys; holograph; published as page 65, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript of "Little Lord Fauntleroy," review of Frances Hodgson Burnett book; holograph, with printed advertisement quoting Alcott and G. P. Lathrop, and containing two of R. B. Birch's illustrations, circa 1886 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alden, Isabella Macdonald
    - Letter to Daniel Lothrop regarding submission of work, 1874 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alger, Horatio
    - Letter to Edward Stratemeyer, regarding Bright Days, [1896?] Sep 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anderson, Alexander
    - Letter from National Academy of Design, regarding election to membership, 1826 Jan 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Scrapbook of pictorial engravings, with portraits of Anderson and his engraved business cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Andersen, H. C. (Hans Christian)
    - Envelope addressed to Horace E. Scudder, and letter to Michael Rosing, mentioning gifts of money from American children, circa 1870, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Scherenschnitte silhouette of two ballerinas in a forest, inscribed by Andersen; framed, circa 1860 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - André, R. (Richard)
    - Drawings (7) for The Butterfly's Ball, by William Roscoe; ink and watercolor on paper mounted on illustration board, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Drawings (15) for By Land & Water; ink and watercolor on paper, dummy, with notes regarding changes, circa 1888
    - Drawings (4): "Santa Claus in the Stable," "Santa Claus in his Library," "Santa Claus in his Workshop," and "Well-Earned Repose"; watercolor on paper mounted on linen, circa 1888
  - Angelo, Valenti
    - Manuscript of The Tale of a Donkey; typescript, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Corrections for The Tale of a Donkey; printed proofs, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Drawings (10) for The Tale of a Donkey; pencil on paper, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Drawings (9) for The Tale of a Donkey; ink and Chinese white on bristol board, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Drawing for dust jacket of The Tale of a Donkey; gouache, ink and colored pencil on bristol board, circa 1965
  - Anglund, Joan Walsh
    - Drawings (12) for In a Pumpkin Shell; ink and pencil on paper, circa 1960
    - Drawings (8) for In a Pumpkin Shell; watercolor on illustration board, circa 1960
  - Arthur, T. S. (Timothy Shay)
    - Letter to Mary L. Clark, regarding "little letters of the violet", 1867 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Attwood, Francis Gilbert
    - Drawing, "Dance of the Fairies," for The Fairies' Festival, by John Witt Randall; ink and wash on illustration board, circa 1894
    - Drawing, "Mrs. Peterkin puts salt into her coffee," for The Peterkin Papers, by Lucretia P. Hale; ink on bristol board, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Austin, Etta Maria and George Lowell
    - Letters (7) from authors regarding permission to publish poems in the anthology Little People of God and What the Poets Have Said of Them, 1873-1874 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      General note
      Includes William Cullen Bryant, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Annie E. Faxon, Henry W. Longfellow (2), Alexander McKenzie, and Joshua D. Robinson
  - Averill, Esther Holden
    - Note to Frederic G. Melcher, regarding Daniel Boone, by Feodor Rojankovsky, 1956 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ballantyne, R. M. (Robert Michael)
    - Manuscript, "A Lecture on Kittens (including Cats)"; holograph, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Barber, Catherine W.
    - Pamphlet, "The Creek Maiden's Revenge"; story clipped from newspaper and bound in wrapper printed with library circulation rules; accompanied by receipt of bookbinder (not clearly related), 1865, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Barr, Amelia Edith Huddleston
    - Contract, copyright papers, and receipt for The Bow of Orange Ribbon, 1886-1893 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew)
    - Letter to Joy, regarding Peter Pan, 1906 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Baum, L. Frank (Lyman Frank)
    - Letter to Susan Willard Flint, on "Ozcot" stationery, 1916 Dec 5 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Beard, Daniel Carter
    - Drawing, "The Moving Star," for "Kite Time"; ink and Chinese white on illustration board mounted on heavy paper, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Published in St. Nicholas Magazine, March 1880
  - Bemelmans, Ludwig and Mimi
    - Artist's dummy for The Castle Number Nine, with four extra pages of text, circa 1937 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Titled by the artist "The Castle No.1"
    - Letters (6) to Leonard Lyons, regarding personal topics, 1943-1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Bennett, Charles H. (Charles Henry)
    - Drawings (4) for The Sad History of Greedy Jem; ink and watercolor on bristol board, with set of variant proof prints (11) possibly for an American edition, circa 1858, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Bensel, Edmund Birckhead
    - Drawing, "Meeting of the prince & enlarged fairy" for The Floating Prince, by Frank R. Stockton; pencil and ink wash on paper, circa 1880
  - Billings, Hammatt
    - Drawings (9) for The House that Jack Built; ink on paper, circa 1840 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Birch, Reginald Bathurst
    - Drawing, "'I've got a great deal to thank your Lordship for,' said Higgins," for Little Lord Fauntleroy, by Frances Hodgson Burnett; ink, pencil, and Chinese white on paper, 1886
    - Drawing, "Mr. Mordaunt held the small hand in his as he looked down at the child's face," for Little Lord Fauntleroy, by Frances Hodgson Burnett; watercolor on illustration board, 1916
  - Birney, Herman H.
    - Drawings (13) for "The Ballad of the Oysterman," by Oliver Wendell Holmes; ink and wash on bristol board, with ink captions, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Published in St. Nicholas Magazine, August 1888
  - Bobbett, Walter
    - Drawing, "The little old man of Dyre"; ink on bristol board, 1884
      Published in St. Nicholas Magazine, December 1884
  - Boutet de Monvel, Bernard
    - Letters (2) to Robert Underwood Johnson of the Century Company, 1910, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Boutet de Monvel, Louis-Maurice
    - Letters (25) to Robert Underwood Johnson and the Century Company, with some contemporary English translations, and a note to Miss Agnes Johnson, 1900-1912, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Illustrations (8) clipped from "Everybody's St. Francis," by Maurice Francis Egan, in the Century Magazine, 1912 May (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Boutet de Monvel, Roger
    - Letters (12) to the Century Company, with contemporary English translations, 1910-1914, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Manuscript, "Lucien Simon"; holograph, in French, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bradley, Will
    - Agreement with Dodd, Mead & Company, regarding Peter Poodle, 1906 May 21 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Bransom, Paul
    - Drawings (6) for The Call of the Wild, by Jack London; ink, pencil, watercolor, and charcoal on paper, circa 1912 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Illustration plate sheets from The Call of the Wild, with letter from Macmillan & Co., 1912, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Drawings (5) for title page for The Wind in the Willows, by Kenneth Grahame; ink and watercolor on paper, circa 1913 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Photograph of Bransom by Tommy Weber, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Bruton, W. (William)
    - Drawing for cover of Afternoon Tea; watercolor and ink on paper, circa 1885 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Drawings (3) for covers of pantomime toy books; ink on tracing paper, circa 1880 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Drawing for poster for pantomime toy books, circa 1880
    - Drawings (20) for Johnny Headstrong's Trip to Coney Island; ink and pencil on bristol board, with publisher's storage portfolio, circa 1882
    - Sketches for "Johnnie Headstrong's Trip to Central Park"; pencil on paper, circa 1882
  - Bulla, Clyde Robert
    - Holiday card to Valenti Angelo, with photographs (2) of Bulla, 1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Burchfield, Charles
    - Drawing, "The Counter-pane Fairy," after Katherine Pyle; gouache on paper, 1913
  - Burgess, Gelett
    Includes Goop parodies by others
    - The Burgess Nonsense Book (1904)
      Many of the drawings first appeared in other publications, but they are filed here by their page number in this volume, subtitled "a Complete Collection of the Humorous Masterpieces of Gelett Burgess"
      - Drawings (84), sketches and final drawings; pencil and ink on paper, bristol board, and illustration board, 1898-1904 (Box 2, Folder 47-50)
    - Goops and How to Be Them (1900)
      Original title: "Goop Babies: A Manual of Manners for Polite Infants"
      - Drawings (15), concept sketches; pencil on paper, circa 1898 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - Drawings (34) for St. Nicholas Magazine; ink, pencil, and watercolor on bristol board, 1898-1900 (Box 3, Folder 52-53)
      - Drawings (93) for book; ink and pencil on bristol board, with paste-up text, 1898-1900 (Box 3, Folder 54-58)
        Dedication page includes self-portrait
    - Goop Tales Alphabetically Told (1904)
      - Sketch for cover; colored pencils on paper, circa 1904 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      - Sketches (38) for pages; pencil on paper, circa 1904 (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
      - Drawing for cover; colored pencil and ink on paper, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 62)
      - Drawings (53) for pages; ink and pencil on bristol board, with paste-up text, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 63-67)
        Drawing number 28 absent from the collection
      - Printed cloth covers (2), 1904 (Box 4, Folder 68-69)
    - Drawings (4) for "An Alphabet of Goop Virtues and Vices"; ink and pencil on bristol board, undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Drawing of Goop Santa Claus; watercolor and ink on illustration board, with Christmas greeting to Jane on verso, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Letter to Carolyn Wells, regarding acrostics, 1932 Dec 24 (Box 4, Folder 72)
      Removed from Shirley 3954
    - Letters (2) to Kate, regarding the Goops and personal topics, 1899, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Manuscript, "The Agnes Magazine"; typescript carbon, with ink and watercolor drawings, and holograph poem; inscribed to Agnes Bouchard, 1898 Jul 15 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Manuscript, "Goopana," parody of Burgess's work by unidentified authors [likely family members or friends], undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Manuscript, "The Most Peculiar History of the Chewing Gum Man"; bound typescript, with ink and watercolor drawings, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 76)